You know, alright, page פ"ה pei hei and we stop, we start
at the top, the very top of the דף, daf, ואמר רבי
יוחנן ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan at the exact first word of the דף.
daf.
So the issue was, if you might remember, that רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish were debating whether when בכורים bikkurim
comes from a less than ideal location, whether they're פטור בדיעבד. patur
bedi'avad. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said yes and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
said no. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish compared it to an animal that
was scrawny. And רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan had a special פסוק pasuk
that no, they're not good, maybe particularly because of the nature of
בכורים. bikkurim. Anyway, so we have a ברייתא baraita that said that
if you bring it from rooftops and from boats and so on,
one ברייתא baraita said you bring and you קורא, korei, which means
you're biblically obligated. The other says you bring and you're not קורא,
korei, which could mean you're rabbinically obligated. So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
is able to deal with it. You bring and you're קורא korei
is his position, you are obligated. And the case where you're not
קורא korei is when it grew from a rooftop that wasn't a
cave roof, but a rooftop, a normal rooftop, which would mean that
it wasn't even properly כבית, kibeit, which meant that it wasn't growing
from the ground of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. But how does רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan deal with the fact that one ברייתא baraita actually
says you bring and you make the declaration, seems to be clearly
that you can make בכורים bikkurim out of such fruit? So let's
take a look. אלא לרבי יוחנן קשיא. Ela le'Rabbi Yochanan kashia. Very
top of פ"ה עמוד א', pei hei amud aleph, the very first
word, okay?
אלא לרבי יוחנן קשיא, Ela le'Rabbi Yochanan kashia, but this is difficult
according to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. What does he do with this
ברייתא baraita that says you can bring from the rooftop and from
the boat and so on and make the declaration? So the גמרא
Gemara says תנאי היא, tannai hi, you're right. It's a debate of
תנאים, tannaim, there is a תנא tanna that disagrees with רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan and says that the בכורים bikkurim is valid, he can't
get out of that. But רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan calls like the
other תנאים. tannaim. דתניא, detanya, anyway, as we taught in the
ברייתא, baraita, שבגג שבחור ומביא וקורא, shebegag shebachur vemevi vekorei, that from
the rooftop and from the again this would have to be a
cave roof, and from an empty lot, you can bring and קורא,
korei, even though these are non-ideal places.
שבקיץ שבספינה אינו מביא כל עיקר. shebakis shebesfina eino mevi kol ikkar.
However, when it comes from the flower pot of the boat, you
can't bring it at all. Either because these are without holes in
them, therefore it's not growing from the land of Israel, or talking
about that maybe this is a degree that it is so non-ideal,
the growing
condition, that even in
there that these would not be good at all, here they are
really completely considered
no such low grade or so inappropriate growing conditions that the בכורים
bikkurim would not be acceptable even בדיעבד. bedi'avad. So what we have
is the following. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says that the בכורים bikkurim
is acceptable בדיעבד bedi'avad even if it grows in non-ideal conditions. רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan saying it is not. We have ברייתות baraitot that
seem to support ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, but רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
claims well no there's a debate of תנאים tannaim and some of
them agree with me, and maybe even those that do say that
they can be good would distinguish between how non-ideal those growing conditions
are. Okay, all of that is within בכורים. bikkurim. Again, our משנה
mishnah was talking about bringing non-ideal flour and there was never a
hint in all this discussion that you aren't יוצא. yotzei. The only
discussion was were you not יוצא yotzei for בכורים bikkurim and partly
as we said could be the whole concept of בכורים bikkurim has
to mean that this is like the choice of your produce, and
of course the point we made was not necessarily the fruit itself
is in its most ideal state as Bobby said correctly the other
day, sometimes those first fruit are a little scrawny, but at least
that it represents the best of your produce, it's coming from the
fruit that grew in these ideal conditions and not in these less
than ideal conditions. Okay, and now it ends up with the previous
משנה, mishnah, וכולן אין באין אלא מן המובחר, vekulan ein ba'in ela
min hamuvchar, and this is now going back again in
direct one hand reinforcing but also in contrast to בכורים, bikkurim, that
the flour only comes from the best places. But again the implication
being and let it be explicit in the next משנה mishnah that
if it is not ideal it is still good.
And now let's take a look and one of the places mentioned,
so it said the
אלפא לסולת, alfa lasolet, the A-grade סולת solet was some of the
places of מכמס וזנוח, Michmas and Zanoach, and the second grade סולת,
solet, right underneath that or A minus was עפראים. Afurayim. So because
משנה mishnah mentions עפראים, Afurayim, the גמרא Gemara finds this as a
nice opportunity to tell a line of אגדתא. aggadeta. So let's take
a look. וכולן אין באין אלא מן המובחר vekulan ein ba'in ela
min hamuvchar and again the second grade was עפראים. Afurayim. So אמרו
ליה יוחנא וממרא למשה. amru lei Yochna u-Mamre le-Moshe. So יוחנא וממרא,
Yochna u-Mamre, I have no idea where the גמרא Gemara came up
with these names from the context what, חרטומי מצרים? Chartumei Mitzrayim? Right,
I know who they are supposed to be, I just don't know
where it came up with the name. So from the context חרטומי
מצרים, Chartumei Mitzrayim, as we are going to see, they are some
of the חרטומים, Chartumim, you know, that
משה Moshe had to compete with. unless of course it had a
מסורה, Masorah, right? Anyway, so they said to משה, Moshe, they said
to משה, Moshe, this is quoted in רש״י, Rashi, it's a great
line, תבן אתה מכניס לעפריים. teven ata machnis l'Ofrayim. Now
I think when רש״י Rashi quotes it, it's למצרים, l'Mitzrayim, okay? But
anyway, are you trying to bring in—I could be wrong, I'd have
to take the רש״י Rashi out—are you trying—are you bringing straw to
עפריים? Ofrayim? It's, you know, the phrase coals to Newcastle. Coal to
Newcastle. Who needs straw in עפריים? Ofrayim? So we just learned that
עפריים Ofrayim was like—was like, you know, the—the A minus, not the
A plus, but the A let's say, just—just the second level of,
you know, where the grain and the wheat would come from for
the מנחות. Menachot. So obviously they had a lot of grain there.
If you've got a lot of grain, you've got a lot of
straw. So anyway, עפריים Ofrayim was a place of grain and straw.
So they were saying to him, who needs your, you know, your—your
magic and your tricks? It's like bringing coals to Newcastle, it's like
bringing straw to עפריים. Ofrayim. So this is what they said to
משה. Moshe. So what did he say back? אמר להו, Amar lehu,
he said back to them, אמרי אינשי, amri inshi, no, people say,
למתא ירקא ירקא שקיל, l'mata yarka yarka shakil, in the place—in the
city of vegetables or the place of vegetables, that's where you should
bring your vegetables, meaning there's a good market for them, and people
are interested in the best products. Rise—this is the way—one of the
commentators explained—the best products rise to the top. If everybody's there buying
vegetables, then, you know, and yours are the best, everybody will go
for yours. So he's basically saying we'll see if, you know, whose—whose,
like, magic is the best, or we'll see if mine is really
magic. It's a great place in a way to prove, you know,
that it is not magic and that it is God. Because if
my—what I do beats what you're doing, it'll prove that what we
did—that what I'm doing is not really magic. Okay, so that was
a nice little digression because we had mentioned עפריים. Ofrayim. Okay, now
the גמרא Gemara goes to the next משנה. Mishnah. And this משנה
Mishnah makes clear what was only clear by implication yesterday, that בדיעבד,
b'diavad, if you do not bring ideal flour, it is still good.
אין מביאים לא מבית הזבלים, Ein mevi'im lo mibeit hazevalim, you do
not bring flour that grew from grain from in a—in a—what's it
called, manured field. Although, you know, the manure is good in order—in
terms of the nutrients, but it makes for apparently smelly or stinky
grain. ולא מבית השלחים, V'lo mibeit hashlachim,
and not from a place that is heavily irrigated. Again, the assumption
being that if it doesn't do well on its own rainwater, it's
not going to be as high quality.
בית הזבלים, Beit hazevalim, that's something that was like, I imagine they
fertilized all their fields, so basically it means like one was really—
Presumably, I don't know if that's necessarily true, Bobby. My—my—
Yeah, go ahead. Okay, I have no idea about the agriculture, go
ahead.
Is that השם Hashem is say, it's gonna come from Me, it's
not gonna come from fertilizing, which we—at garden, you go and fertilize,
and it's not come by extra water.
It has to be natural.
And that's the—the אמונה. emunah. Where it came from. You don't have
to help Me.
Okay, that's nice. Now the question is, I should say—now Michael's question
is,
is that does everybody fertilize? And I don't think so. I think
some fields can grow by their natural—I don't know, is that true?
Do you have to actively fertilize some fields?
Farmers fertilize— Well, I'm saying, they probably did then, and if the
problem was what it is—irrigation is an extra— But
everything needs a certain amount of external fertilization,
isn't that what they probably did anyway? But it has to be
natural, like it's—it's grown—like a compost. Right. It doesn't have to be
זבל.
zevel. Oh, that's like, specifically manure. Not—you're saying quantity, but the thing
is that maybe it's manure as opposed to other types of fertilizer.
Also, as fields get used,
the soil gets depleted. Right. So imagine that the soil should be
getting depleted, but it isn't.
Right. Well, that actually is going to be a little bit later
about the rotating of crops or what have you, we'll see that.
So that's all very interesting. Now your point also, Bobby, about, like,
well anyway, I would say this, there's an interesting question here where
רש״י Rashi consistently reads this as talking—as talking about, maybe because of
the plural language, maybe because of the last פרק perek and other
things, that we're talking specifically about the communal מנחות, Menachot, we're talking
about the עומר Omer and the שתי הלחם, Shtei Halechem, where those
are really
like—they're בכורים, Bikkurim, so it actually fits in a little bit to
the—to the previous discussion. Those are representing like the—the choice of the
crops and you want them to be the things that are, you
know, the most select, and not have these problems, either second grade
or as you say,
more—too much human input or whatever, how we understand it. תוספות Tosafot
understands that we're talking actually about grain for all of the מנחות,
Menachot, we're not limiting ourselves to עומר Omer and שתי הלחם. Shtei
Halechem.
Okay, it seems to say that it's about the field. דלא צריכה
לזבל, De lo tzericha l'zabel, means that you could do it without
fertilizing it— Oh,
you mean that you're reading the רש״י Rashi that it was a
field— Which is supposed to be the real רש"י Rashi has two
explanations. The first explanation is what you said, a field that needs
a field that needs fertilizing and therefore maybe it did not get
enough fertilizer and it's not good. And then the second thing רש"י
Rashi says is שזבלה מבאישה ומקלקל טעם הפירות, Shezevela mav'isha umekalkel ta'am
haperot,
that the heavy, you know, dung actually affects the taste of what
grows. So, but that's the point I'd forgotten to mention that the
first explanation in רש"י Rashi is that it needs fertilization and not
giving it, so it's not as high quality. Okay, so these types
of things are not as high quality and you can't use them
for again, either all מנחות Menachot or at least for the עומר
Omer and the שתי הלחם. Shtei Halechem. ולא מדי אילן Velo midei
ilan and not from a grain field that had trees growing among
it, assuming it's not כלאים Kilayim or even if it was כלאים
Kilayim it doesn't make the fruit forbidden, but anyway because because the
competition with the trees means that the grain is not getting the
requisite nutrients. ואם הביא כשר, Ve'im hevi kasher, בדיעבד bedi'avad all of
this is כשר. kasher. So again you see in contrast to the
debate of רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש Rabbi Yochanan veReish Lakish by ביכורים,
Bikurim, here we say that even these non-ideal grains will בדיעבד bedi'avad
be okay.
Why would it be כלאים? Kilayim?
What? If you space it appropriately it won't be כלאים Kilayim or
if you put up a little fences or whatever you could do.
Okay, כיצד Keitzad now, כיצד הוא עושה, Keitzad hu oseh, now how,
here you go Bobby, here's the rotating of the crops. What is
the way to get the best grain to use and to use
for either at least עומר שתי הלחם, Omer Shtei Halechem, maybe for
all מנחות? Menachot? ניר השנה, Nira hashana, one year you you overturn
the the field but you leave it fallow. So ניר Nir does
not mean just not plant, it means that you actually plow it
but you don't plant. So so you turn over the soil בשנה
ראשונה, bashana rishona, that's year one. ובשנה שנייה, Uvashana shniya, in year
two, זרעה קודם לפסח שבעים יום, zar'ah kodem lePesach shiv'im yom, you
plant it seventy days before פסח, Pesach, so that after it's growing
it's growing just as, you know, it's getting into the spring and
the weather is getting hot and presumably that's the best time to
be planting it. והוא עושה סולת מרובה, Vehu oseh solet meruba, and
it makes a lot of, you know, of flour for the amount
of grain. So the so each stalk has a lot of grain
and and is a very high yield. Okay, so that's the best
way to do it. Now, again the question here is, are we
talking about all מנחות? Menachot? We might be talking about all מנחות
Menachot because still קודם פסח kodem Pesach is not because of the
עומר, Omer, קודם פסח kodem Pesach might just be that the spring
and that's the time when it's good to plant is right before
the spring and so on. Okay, so it could be we're talking
about again the best way to make grain for all מנחות Menachot
or we might be talking specifically about the עומר, Omer, it's ambiguous.
רש"י ותוספות Rashi veTosafot disagree about that. All right.
כיצד בודק את הקמח, Keitzad bodek et hakemach, I guess
how do you check it to make sure that it's been, like,
well-sifted? הגזבר מכניס ידו לתוכה, Hagizbar machnis yado letocha,
the גזבר, gizbar, the temple treasurer when you bring the flour to
be used now again this raises the question, right? Are you making
it at home or are you making it in the בית המקדש?
Beit Hamikdash? If it is talking about the עומר, Omer, then you
understand that's made in the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, so the גזבר
gizbar has a chance to inspect the flour. If you're making it
at home though and it's other מנחות Menachot which you might again
it's unclear, you might have been able to make it at home,
you might have needed to make it in the בית המקדש, Beit
Hamikdash, it's unclear then how does the גזבר gizbar check the flour?
Okay, so let's see how the גזבר gizbar is checking it. מכניס
ידו לתוכה, Machnis yado letocha, he sticks his hand into the flour.
עלה באבק פסולה, Ala be'avak psula, if he when he comes brings
takes it out there's some dust or dirt that's sticking to his
hand, it's invalid, it's not sifted well enough עד שינפה, ad sheyinafe,
until
it is sifted. It has to be sifted to remove all of
these impurities and then it will be כשר. kasher. ואם התליעה, Ve'im
hitli'a, but if it's became wormy, פסולה, psula, then it's invalid, you
can't just remove the worms and make it כשר. kasher. Right, once
it became wormy you have to throw it all out. Now again
the phrase by the way of פסולה psula is interesting. It doesn't
sound like ideally it should be completely sifted. It says if it's
if it's got some impurities, it's invalid until it's sifted, which is
quite quite interesting, which means that if it comes from this second-grade
grain בדיעבד bedi'avad it's okay, you know, from the irrigated, what do
you call it, manured field, that's בדיעבד bedi'avad okay. But if there
are some impurities, until you remove those impurities, until you remove freely
remove all the dirt and the dust, it's going to be invalid.
That's pretty interesting. And again the question is, are we talking about
a normal מנחה Mincha or are we talking about the עומר? Omer?
By the עומר Omer we learned that you have the, you know,
thirteen sieves and all of this. So okay, that you that we've
already seen and that also explains why the גזבר gizbar has a
chance to inspect the flour because it's being done in the בית
המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. But if you're talking about your private מנחה, Mincha,
you know, this would be a surprise that that would be the
sort of the level of purity that would be required. And it
would also mean that the
גזבר gizbar would...
No, I was just so surprised that wormy flour could be פסול.
Pasul.
Wormy not, but dust, עוב, ov, which you know like some small
impurity, it doesn't even take like your pebble, dust, you know? So
that I do think that that is surprise. It is פסול, Pasul,
meaning yes it says you can fix it, but until you fix
it, the language being used is פסול, Pasul, okay? It's invalid. So
let's see now the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא's Gemara going to focus
a lot on the rotating of the crops. Let's take a look.
כיצד עושה, Keitzad ose, what would you do to get this top
grade flour? ניר שנה ראשונה, Nira shana rishona, you turn over the
soil the first year, and then you plant it the second year.
So איבעיא להו, Ibayah lehu, היכי קאמר, Heichi ka’amar, how is it
saying? ניר שנה ראשונה ושנייה, Nira shana rishona u'shniya, you turn over
the soil the first year and the second year. I'm sorry, I
put the comma in the wrong place. ניר שנה ראשונה, Nira shana
rishona, you turn over the soil the first year, ושנייה ניר וזרע,
u'shniya nira u'zra, and the second year you turn over the soil
and you plant it. Meaning that there the turning over the soil
is the normal... I'm sorry, okay, I got it right the first
time. So you turn it over the first year and you turn
it over the second year and then you plant it. That's one
possibility. או דלמא, O dilma, or maybe it's saying ניר שנה ראשונה,
Nira shana rishona, you turn over the soil year one, ושנייה זרע
בלא ניר, u'shniya zra belo nira, and the second year you just
plant without overturning the soil, which is what the משנה Mishna sounded
like. The משנה Mishna said you turn over the soil the first
year, you plant it the second year. But the גמרא Gemara is
saying is maybe it means the first year you just turn over
the soil and the second year you turn it over and you
plant it. Now רש"י Rashi points out though that don't confuse turning
over with plowing. When you plant you're always going to make furrows
and plant at the moment of planting. That's included in the word
זרע. zra. The question here is would there be, but that takes
place as we've seen towards the springtime, like you know seventy days
before פסח. Pesach. But from the beginning of the year would you
do a whole process of turning over the soil? That's the question.
So year one you turn over the soil, you don't plant at
all, year two you're going to plant with plowing and planting, but
will there also be a turning over the soil that will precede?
And again, this is the way to create this ideal grain to
be used for again either all מנחות menachos or at least the
עומר omer and the שתי הלחם.
shtei halechem. You would think the turning over the soil checks your...
aerates the soil and allows the seed to... permeate... better way.
Even before the plowing.
Meaning
רש"י Rashi is saying of course you're going to make furrows to
plant, right, I mean I didn't mean right, but but the question
is would you also do a whole turning over the soil? So
you're saying it makes a lot of sense even if you did
it the first year. Okay, so that's going to be the גמרא's's
Gemara question now for a good section of today's דף. daf. So
let's take a look. תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear, דתניא,
detanya, it was
taught in a ברייתא, braisa, אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yose, Rabbi
Yose says, אף חיטי קרזיים וכפר אחים, Af chitei karzayim u'kfar achim,
even these two places called חיטי קרזיים Chitei Karzayim and the village
of אחים, Achim, the village of brothers,
אלמלא סמוכות לירושלים, ilmalei smuchos l'Yerushalayim, had they just been closer to
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, היו מביאים מהם, hayu mevi'im mehem, they would bring have
brought from them the עומר omer and the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem.
But the point is is that we've learned before you know that
you try to bring the עומר omer from as close to ירושלים
Yerushalayim as possible. So therefore because these were a little distant, they
were not able to be brought from there, but otherwise they would
have been ideal places to bring the עומר omer and the שתי
הלחם. shtei halechem. Why? לפי שאין מביאים את העומר אלא מן השדות
המדרומות, Lefi she'ein mevi'im es ha'omer ela min hasados hamidromos,
you only bring the עומר omer from the southern fields. Now what
does southern mean? רש"י Rashi says it means south of ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
but תוספות, Tosafos, what do I care for south of ירושלים? Yerushalayim?
תוספות Tosafos says it means it has the southern exposure, that it's
on a hill and it's on a slant so that it faces
the south and gets all the sun from the south, because the
sun especially in the spring and leading into the summer months goes
into the south and is at the heat of the day in
the south, okay? And therefore it's getting all of the sun in
the south. Water also drains, but that's however it's slanted, water would
drain. Why do we want facing the south? is the question. So
it's for the sun and the גמרא Gemara will make that clear.
Okay, but תוספות Tosafos says it means the southern exposure essentially, southern
slant, it does not mean south of ירושלים Yerushalayim because who cares
where it's south? Okay, anyway,
והמנונרות, ve'hamenunaros, so that's from the word ניר nir which was the
word in our משנה, mishna, ניר nir I should say, which means
overturn soil. So those are the things you want, that the soil
has been overturned, which is in our משנה, mishna, and that it's
facing south, and that gets you the most ideal. Now because again
this is about the עומר, omer, so therefore it reinforces the read
of the משנה mishna that the משנה's's mishna concern is about the
עומר omer and the discussion is about the עומר. omer. On the
other hand תוספות Tosafos points out that one of the places is
called חיטי... chitei... what was it called?
חיטי קרזיים. Chitei Karzayim. The wheat. You don't bring the עומר omer
from wheat. But תוספות Tosafos says oh you know, but maybe it
was just the name of the place. Maybe we're bringing barley from
it but it happened to be the name of the place. Anyway
here we're talking clearly about the עומר omer which raises the question:
is the whole discussion about the עומר, omer, or is the discussion
about all מנחות, menachos, and that's really ambiguous. Okay anyway, you would
have brought the עומר omer from here had they been closer to
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. לפי
שאין מביאים את העומר אלא מן השדות המד... Lefi she'ein mevi'im es
ha'omer ela min hasados hamid... of growing grain for the
עומר. Omer. And why is it but או דילמא, o dilma, I
mean like whatever. Apparently, like ideally. I don't know if they really,
yeah I don't know how important the לכך lekach word is, although
רש״י Rashi does say that what were you saying?
The מדרש Midrash that I showed you from רבה Rabba said that
they were bringing it from בית לחם Beit Lechem and that's why
they were all out.
Oh, in בית לחם? Beit Lechem?
And was בית לחם Beit Lechem
closer to ירושלים Yerushalayim than these places? I don't know. That's a
good question. רש״י Rashi also makes it sound like these places were
very close to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, that were in like the valley, that
were in the mountains that were around ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So they, it
seems to be like they were pretty close.
Okay, yeah רש״י Rashi says here לשם עומר leshem Omer by the
ניר. nir. So again, I doubt that that was מעכב, me'akev, but
maybe it was ideally that they were actually over, even overturning the
soil for that. But that is how רש״י Rashi handles the word
לכך. lekach. Yep. So anyway, okay. So let's take a look.
First of all, this came from somebody's private field. That's why I
was wondering, you know, if when at the very beginning, came from
like a temple owned field or from,
yeah,
it's
not somebody's private field, but it could mean, you know, he's overturning
it in the potentiality that someone's going to want to take the
עומר Omer from it.
Maybe it's a nice זכות, zechut, but you're right. It never said
that the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash owned the field. It always makes
it sound like we look around to see where we can get
the עומר Omer from. It's also not, you know, it's not a
good investment of money to buy fields. All you need is a
few of a little bit of grain. Somebody will obviously want to
donate it if, you know, so, but yeah, it does not sound
that they ever owned these fields. But you're right. It becomes funny
that I'm going to have to turn it over לשם כך. leshem
kach. Uh-huh. So the לכך lekach word is funny here, but רש״י
Rashi takes it seriously.
What else does he say? That רש״י Rashi only knows that the,
that עין כלוחית Ein Kluchit is surrounded by hills because of the
פסוק. pasuk.
Great. What else? And he also knows that the grain grows well
in the hills because of another פסוק pasuk if you keep on
reading the רש״י. Rashi. Exactly. All right. So that's how I know
most of my agriculture from the גמרא. Gemara. Anyway, all right.
Anyway, okay.
So therefore, anyway רש״י Rashi is saying that these places were in
the hills near ירושלים Yerushalayim where you have very nice grain and
it's exposed to the sun, but because it's a little distance they
did not bring it. And because ideally, but ideally you could have
brought it from here. These would have been perfect because they're facing
the south and because the soil was turned over for this sake.
המנונרות לכך. hamenunarot lekach. שבהן חמה זורחת, shebahen chama zorachat,
that in those sites the fields the sun shines, ומהן חמה שוקעת,
umehen chama shoka'at,
and from them the sun sets. I mean, I assume the sun
sets everywhere, but it basically means that the sun is, they get
exposure for most of the sunlight of the day. They're exposed to
the entire sunlight and they get sun the entire day. כיצד עושה,
keitzad oseh, what would you do? How would you deal with these,
you know sort of rotate the crops? נירש שנה ראשונה, nirash shana
rishona,
you let it lay fallow, but again not fallow, really means המנונרות
hamenunarot is overturned the soil and lay fallow for the first year.
ושנייה, ushniya, and in the second year, חורש, choresh, you plow it,
ושונה, veshoneh, and you plow it again. So you've overturned the soil
and then a second time you do the furrowing for the sake
of וזרע, vezara, the planting. So it's very explicit. The second year
you overturn the soil and then a second time you do the
furrows for the sake of the planting. קודם לפסח שבעים יום, kodem
lePesach shiv'im yom, 70 days before פסח, Pesach, כדי שתהא סמוכה לחמה,
kedei shetehei smucha lechama, so that it should be close to when
the sun starts getting sunny, right? Because near the spring is when
it starts becoming sunny. So you want the plants to be growing
during the sunny period. So you plant it 70 days before פסח.
Pesach. ועושה קנה זרת ושיבולת זרתיים. ve'oseh kaneh zeret veshibolet zartayim.
And this becomes such great grain that this was before they had
the super crops and those GMO, you know, whatever things, that the
height of the stalk is a זרת. zeret. A זרת zeret is
two טפחים, tefachim, it's like from your thumb to your pinky when
you spread it out. And the height of the, of the, of
the,
not the stalk, what's do you call the stuff on top of
the stalk? The ear? Whatever, the stuff that actually has the grain.
That's two of these. So it's a two to one ratio of
the ear to the stalk. I don't know if such a thing
ever exists, but that anyway they might be exaggerating, but that's the
way of saying you're going to get an extremely high yield of
grain if you follow this advice.
Okay. וקוצר, vekotzer, and then you harvest it, ומעמר, ume'amer, you pile
it, ודש, vedash, it's like we're learning שבת, Shabbat, now these are
all the stages, מלאכות melachot of שבת. Shabbat. Anyway, you thresh it,
וזורה, vezoreh, and you winnow it, ובורר, uborer, and you select out
the bad, the winnowing gets out the chaff, the natural chaff, the
בורר borer gets out like the pebbles and the other, you know,
impurities, וטוחן, vethochen, you grind it, ומרקד, umeraked, and you sift it,
ומביא אצל גזבר, umevi etzel gizbar, now you bring this great flour
to the גזבר, gizbar, וגזבר מכניס ידו לתוכה, vegizbar machnis yado letocha,
he'll stick his hand in it, אם עלה בה אבק, im alah
bah avak, if some dust came up
it was פסול pasul for the עומר. Omer.
Yeah, because it's mentioned the עומר Omer earlier and because it's also,
right, stylizing the whole process. It makes it sound like it was
a big to-do. That is true, but I wanted to point out
a problem תוספות Tosafot asks about this in a minute. Anyway he
sticks in his hand, אם עלתה בו אבק הסמדק, im alta bo
avak hasemadak, if some dust comes out, אומר לו, omer lo, he
says, חזור ונפולה שנייה, chazor unifola sheniya,
go sift it a second time. רבי נתן Rabbi Natan אומר, omer,
here's how he would test it for impurities: גזבר שך ידו שמן,
gizbar sach yado shemen, he puts, he, you know,
he smears his hand with oil, he oils his hand, ומכניס לתוכה,
umachnis letocha, until he brings up all the dust. He's not just
an inspector, he also tries to solve the problem. So he sticks
his hand in and all of the dust or whatever impurity, it
sticks to his hand. I don't know why they stick to the
hand and not the flour, but okay. Anyway, that's how you would
do it. Now, Michael says, I think correctly, it mentioned the עומר,
Omer, it speaks about this whole huge process, it sounds like it's
all for the sake of the עומר. Omer. תוספות Tosafot is though
a little bit bothered, because תוספות Tosafot said if that, when it
comes
that, trying to remember that when it speaks about
one of these stages, hold on.
First of all, he's bothered because by the עומר Omer we're always
mentioning שלוחי בית דין shluchei beit din and not the גזבר, gizbar,
but besides that he had another question. He said, oh, that this
דש, dash, that you thresh it,
and when we discussed the עומר Omer we said that you didn't
thresh it like that, that you actually took the stalks and you
beat the stalks, which isn't threshing.
So that was, so that wasn't part of the process of the
עומר Omer as we had described earlier did not involve a traditional
threshing. So תוספות Tosafot was bothered with that.
So again, there, so that's why he thinks that we're not limiting
ourselves to the עומר. Omer. We mentioned the עומר Omer but we're
not limiting ourselves. That's the ongoing ambiguity here, whether we're talking about
the עומר Omer or מנחה. mincha. Anyway, back to our point, תני
התם, tani hatam, so we taught nonetheless, meaning that's what you say
after you quote a long ברייתא braita but you're only interested in
one line. We taught nonetheless, חורש ושונה, choresh veshoneh,
that you plow and then you plow again in the second year.
So you see there was an overturning of soil. So the גמרא
Gemara says ולטעמך, uletamecha, according to you, מתניתין
לא תני שונה, matnitin lo tani shona, if you're trying to prove,
so maybe you're right, that ברייתא braita has an overturning of soil
in the second year. But it didn't say it in our משנה.
mishnah. Our משנה mishnah says you overturn the first year, you plant
the second. So at best I'll say it's a debate of the
ברייתא braita and משנה. mishnah. That doesn't prove what the משנה mishnah
means. So ברייתא קתני שונה braita katani shona and our ברייתא braita
does say שונה, shona, so it doesn't, so if anything it maybe
means that the משנה mishnah doesn't mean that. So the גמרא Gemara
says הא לא קשיא, ha lo kashya, that's not difficult. כאן בעבודה
כאן בשאינה עבודה. kan ba-avoda kan beshe-eina avoda. That I could say
the following. I could say that
if you're dealing with a field that is already
had been already sort of plowed and threshed and worked, etc., in
previous
years, then the standards would be different, whether you would need to
overturn the soil the second year. Now, you would think actually, I
might think that if it had been עבודה avoda in the sense
of had been, you know, worked in the past, maybe there's more
of a need to overturn the soil because it's more depleted the
soil. But רש"י Rashi seems to say that we're saying no, if
it's עבודה avoda means that it had already been sort of plowed
before I got started. So when I enter into the first year,
if it had already been plowed once, then I'll only overturn the
soil one more time. But if when I entered into the first
year
it had not been plowed yet, then I'll overturn the soil twice,
once in the first year and once in the second year, to
get a sum total of twice. So that's how the גמרא Gemara
gets out of it. Maybe in the end, you know, you would
only overturn the soil in the second year. You're trying to get
two overturnings before the plowing,
okay? And the משנה mishnah that doesn't mention it is because there
was an overturning before you started.
It wouldn't hurt anyway to overturn it the second year no matter
what.
Look, you got to see, you know, this is an interesting thing
about learning the דף, daf, how the גמרא Gemara can go from
discussing like the most complex legal issues, you know, to the most
almost mundane fact questions about did they overturn it once or twice.
So I mean draw from that whatever sort of theological or religious
significance you will, but you don't get a sense in the גמרא
Gemara that it's taking this conversation any less seriously than it takes,
you know, a very complex legal conversation. Okay, so now let's see
מאי הוי עלה, mai hava ala, what was the conclusion? תא שמע,
ta shema, come and hear, דתניא, detanya, as
we have a ברייתא, braita, you'll just be tested, you know, you
did.
Alright, but we want to know what, oh, that's true, that's true.
Anyway, ניר חציה וזורע
חציה. nir chatziya vezoreia chatziya. So now we're going to talk about
a field, but in a field you don't just not plant at
all on any given year. You're rotating crops, which means that you're
doing one thing for half of your field and the other thing
for the other half of the field. So here it explicitly spells
it out more clearly. You've got a field, side A of your
field you are laying fallow, which means you're overturning the soil.
Side B you're planting. So that's what you do. ניר חציה וזורע
חציה, ניר חציה וזורע חציה. nir chatziya vezoreia chatziya, nir chatziya vezoreia
chatziya.
And then in the other year you're reversing it. You're planting side
A and you're overturning side B. So what does that prove? Presumably
what it proves is that every year you're alternating overturning planting, overturning
and planting, and it's not mentioning any idea of a second overturning.
It sounds like you would not overturn it a second time.
Every year you do, until you have overturned it twice.
No, no, no. This year I plant side A and I overturn
side B. Next year I overturn side A and I plant side
B, right? And then I keep on reversing planting and overturning. So
there's no sense of doing a double overturning. Okay, again, there's no
sense in the משנה Mishna either, but we wanted to read it
in. So I'm not so sure why this is any more convincing.
Okay, anyways, that's in terms of how you rotate your field, to
rotate—not really rotate your crops—how you rotate your field in order to
get the
best grain, and the best grain to produce the best flour, minimally
for the עומר שתי הלחם, Omer shtei halechem, but maybe even for
all מנחות.
menachot. Can you plow in—in שמיטה Shmita if you're not going to
plant?
So we discussed that yesterday. Actually, no, it said that there you
would just do שביתה. shevita. There were other things that you would
maybe—also for the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, you're not going to actually
plow—you
plow, yes, not plant, yes. Yes, that yes. And we said yesterday
that there are two possible reasons. One, it says maybe it's just
an override, like you can do it on שבת, Shabbat, you can
do it on שמיטה. Shmita. But the other reason, which was more
interesting, was that some of the prohibitions might be more prohibitions of
exerting private ownership. And when it's done for communal purposes and not
as a way of exerting private ownership, that it would not be
a problem. So in this way it might be allowed to harvest
it, it might be allowed to plow—not you, שלוחי בית דין. shluchei
Beit Din. שלוחי בית דין shluchei Beit Din go out, they protect
the field over שמיטה, Shmita, they plow. So either it's because of
an override or because it's not about private ownership.
Even though this is your field, which we're saying in
the—your field, but בית דין Beit Din has taken over, meaning that's
the great theme of שמיטה. Shmita. I'm not, you know, exerting my
private ownership, בית דין Beit Din has taken it over. Okay, now
the גמרא Gemara goes on. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, says
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, אין מביאין את העומר אלא מן השדות המודרמות.
Ein mevi’in et ha’Omer ela min hasadot hamudramot. So
this—it's funny here that we just had it as a ברייתא braita
and now it's coming as a statement of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
as an אמורא. Amora. That does happen sometimes, that Amoraic statements and
ברייתות braitot get sort of, you know, mixed up or duplicated. So
אין מביאין את העומר אלא מן השדות המודרמות, Ein mevi’in et ha’Omer
ela min hasadot hamudramot,
the southern ones שבארץ ישראל, shebe’Eretz Yisrael, שבהן חמה זורחת, shebehen chama
zorachat,
that the sun rises... shines on them ומהם חמה שוקעת, umehem chama
shoka’at,
which presumably just means they get all the sunlight of the day.
תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly. אבא שאול אומר,
Abba Shaul omer, עומר Omer היה בא מביקת בית מקלה. haya ba
mibik’at Beit Makle. So the עומר Omer would come from this place
called the Valley of בית מקלה. Beit Makle. כבת ג' סאין. Kevat
gimmel se’in. It was three סאין se’in wide, this place. Now, three
סאין, se’in, we have been used to as a volume measurement. It
is also a measure of area, like an acre, you know, would
be used to measure an area particularly of fields. And now, I
do not know—I'm sure maybe there's a גמרא Gemara somewhere I'm forgetting,
anyway, if there's a statement
about what is soon to be the yield per סאה se’ah of
a field, per acre, you know, what's the standard yield. I do
think it is interesting that if you remember, the עומר Omer would
come from three סאין se’in of wheat that they would then, you
know, sift down and process to get one-tenth of that amount in
terms of flour. So they—you would start with three סאין se’in as
a volume measurement of wheat, and here it is saying it is
coming from a field that is three סאין, se’in, הסאה hase’ah here
being an area measurement, you know, so it might be an assumption
that a סאה se’ah of land, an acre, produces a סאה—it's se’ah
the same word, but obviously a very different measurement—of wheat. Okay, so
anyway it would come from this place which
was—precisely, service. Right.
So—so it would come from a place of שלוש סאין היתה, shalosh
se’in haita, this שדה מודרמות היתה, sadeh mudramot haita, it was a
southern exposure field. ובא חמה זורחת וממנה חמה שוקעת, Uva chama zorachat
umimena chama shoka’at, the sun would rise and set there. ניר חציה
וזורע חציה, Nir chetzya vezoreia chetzya,
they would alternate the years, one—you know—one year they would have side
A which would be overturned and side B which would be planted.
ניר חציה וזורע חציה Nir chetzya vezoreia chetzya and the other years
they would reverse it. רב חלקיא בר טובי Rav Hilkiya bar Tuvi
הוה ליה קרנא דארעא. hava lei karna de’ar’a. רב חלקיא בר טובי
Rav Hilkiya bar Tuvi had a little corner of his field. ניר
חציה וזורע חציה ניר חציה וזורע חציה. Nir chetzya vezoreia chetzya nir
chetzya vezoreia chetzya. So he decided, I know, either to do an
experiment to see if this worked or maybe he wasn't even really
a farmer, you know, but whatever he was doing, for whatever reason
he did it in a corner of his field, he did this—this
alternating of planting and overturning. ועבדא חד תרי, Ve’avda chad terei, it
produced double the normal yield, like the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא Gemara
likes where the ear is twice as big as the stalk. Double
the normal yield. ומזבין להו לחיטי דסמידה. Umazbin lehu lechitei desmida. He
would sell the wheat for סמידה, smida, which רש"י Rashi says—I don't
know where the etymology of the word, but רש"י Rashi says that
that means for מנחות. menachot. So here, you know, this was choice
grain and he would sell it for מנחות. menachot. So here again
you're getting the ambiguity, are we talking about עומר Omer or are
we talking about general מנחות, menachot, because it ends by a story
of somebody who—who did this, got these results and sold it for
grain for מנחות. menachot.
But the thing is that, you know, they did it precisely, let's
say something happens to part of your field and you're stuck because
you need
three—well, בדיעבד, bedi’avad, if you did it with less, then you'd be
יוצא. yotzei. Why would you—I understand money, give yourself a margin of
error.
Anyway, I think also, if this is your part of your field,
it sounds like giving up all over to the בית המקדש Beit
Hamikdash because it's...
But first of all, didn't say whose field it was. It says,
it would come from this
place.
Yeah, no, so meaning, but if it's my field and I'm giving
it all to the בית המקדש...
Beit Hamikdash... You're right. It goes back to your question. Was it
owned privately? Did the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash take priority over this
field? It's very unclear. You know, you're right. There's a lot that's
not being said. Okay, now we go to the wormy
stuff. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: סולת שהתליאה רובה פסולה. Solet she-hitlia ruba
psula. So if the flour—sorry, no. So if the—now when we said
that you cannot just, you know, remove the bad part, you can
sort of resift it if you need to if it has impurities,
but if it's wormy, you've got to throw it out. Here we're
saying wormy means majority wormy, not just a little wormy. סולת שהתליאה
רובה פסולה. Solet she-hitlia ruba psula. If it's majority wormy, then it's
invalid, you have to throw it all out. וחטים שהתליאו רובם פסולה.
Ve-chittin she-hitliau rubam psula. Even if it's not yet flour, let's say
your wheat gets wormy, you have to throw it all out. But
it's only if it's the majority. So בעא רבי ירמיה: Baya Rebbe
Yirmiya: so now that you're saying majority, but presumably if it's the
minority, you just throw out the bad and keep the good. My
wife and I often have these debates. I don't know if this
is basically a man thing. Like, you know, okay, a few pieces
of bread got moldy, so throw out those bits, the rest is
totally fine!
Who do you think you are?
Well, about mold, right. I think maybe take a little time to
study mold.
Well, so you take out like two more slices but the stuff
in the back has got to be totally fine. Anyway, so here
you see that if the—I got my
proof, as long as it's only the minority that's wormy, right, you
throw that out, the rest is okay. So anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says but wait, we have a question. So בעא רבי ירמיה:
Baya Rebbe Yirmiya: ברוב חטים או ברוב סאה? Be-rov chittin o be-rov
se'ah? What do you mean majority wormy? Does it mean that each,
each, like, you know, each, each piece of flour—I don't even have
pieces of flour—but let's say each grain, the majority of it is
wormy? Or you mean that even if some grains are totally okay,
some of the flour's totally okay, but the majority of the other—you
know, but fifty-one percent of the grains are wormy, then you can't
use the other forty-nine percent. So you see, that's the
debate my wife
and I have.
If every piece of, if every piece of bread was majority wormy,
was majority moldy, I wouldn't try to preserve the little pieces. But
if some of the bread is moldy, you take the rest. So
that's his question. Let's say some of the grain is wormy, some
of the grain is totally untouched, can you preserve the rest? So
the גמרא Gemara says תיקו. Teiku. At least we're not the only
ones who argue. But when I do it, it's only minority, so...
So anyway, alright, now בעא רבא: Baya Rava: so רבא Rava asked,
הקדישן מהו שילקה עליהן משום בעל מום? Hiktishan mahu she-yilke aleihen mishum
Ba'al Mum? Let's say you sanctified this wormy grain. So if you
sanctify an animal that has a מום, mum, a blemish, you transgress
a prohibition. You're not allowed to be מקדיש—not makdish only are you
not allowed to bring an animal, you're not allowed to be מקדיש
makdish an animal that has a מום. mum. So he wants to
know, which is in a way also an interesting question of saying,
where do we ever see that this type of grain is invalid?
The תורה Torah never says, like, it has to be the best
grain or it has to be this. How do we know it's
invalid? So presumably, okay, so maybe inappropriate, but like really invalid? So
presumably it's by some analogy to the idea of a בעל מום,
Ba'al Mum, of a blemish, as applied to grain. So he says,
well, how far does that analogy go? Would you really get lashes
if you tried to sanctify it the same way you do if
you sanctify an animal with a blemish? So that's his question. Why
would you do that? Disrespectful doesn't mean you get lashes.
Okay, so what would you do then?
Right, no, so you don't get lashes, you can't use it but
you don't get lashes for it. So בעא רבא: Baya Rava: so
anyway it says בעא רבא הקדישן מהו שילקה עליהן משום בעל מום?
Baya Rava hiktishan mahu she-yilke aleihen mishum Ba'al Mum? Do you get
lashes for a בעל מום? Ba'al Mum? כיון דפסול כבעל מום דמי.
Keivan de-pasul ke-Ba'al Mum dami. Since it's invalid,
it must be that we're comparing it to a בעל מום. Ba'al
Mum. או דילמא, O dilma, or do we say, no, technically אין
בעל מום אלא בבהמה, ein Ba'al Mum ela be-behemah, there's only a
concept of blemish in a בהמה. behemah. So we're not saying it's
כשר, kasher, so yes, the analogy takes us so far to say
that it's not כשר, kasher, but not to call it a מום
mum to say that you would get lashes. So the גמרא Gemara
says תיקו, Teiku, we don't know the answer.
What, somewhat of a פגם pgam what happens, not a בעל מום?
Ba'al Mum?
Right. Yeah, I don't think you're עובר. over. I think it has
to be דווקא davka those parameters of an animal with a מום.
mum.
הקדיש Hikdish like a שור shor that's a בעל מום, Ba'al Mum,
then then you'd be עובר over
because it's in the פרשה. parasha. Right, correct. Okay, sort of like
the problems with פיגול, Piggul, it's when you're in the פרשה parasha
and you're off as opposed to totally missing the boat. Okay, תנן
התם. Tnan hatam. Now we're going to just apply the same discretion
by wheat to other things that are put on the מזבח. mizbe'ach.
And so, remember you put—you can donate wood to go on the
מזבח, mizbe'ach, and there's a question: does it go on the מזבח
mizbe'ach as a type of קרבן korban or does it go on
the מזבח mizbe'ach as the firewood? There's actually an opinion that if
you donate wood, you need other wood to put it on because
it becomes a type of a קרבן. korban. So let's take a
look. כל עץ שנמצא בו Kol etz she-nimtza bo כל עץ שנמצא
בו תולעת Kol etz shenimtza bo tola'at if you have a piece
of wood that has a worm תולעת, tola'at, פסול לגבי מזבח, pasul
legabei Mizbeach, you can't use it on the מזבח. Mizbeach. Now presumably
that just means as firewood. אמר שמואל לא שנו אלא לח, Amar
Shmuel lo shanu ela lach,
that's only moist because then if it becomes wormy you can't get
out all the worms or it infects the whole piece, אבל ביבש,
aval beyavesh, if it's dry wood, גוררו וכשר, gorero vechasher, then you
can just cut out the wormy part and use the rest. So
for firewood maybe it's not as bad as for a מנחה. mincha.
Okay. So בעי רבא, ba'i Rava, so Rava says, הקדישו, hikdisho, same
question, מהו שילקה עליו משום בעל מום? mahu sheyilke alav mishum ba'al
mum? Same question. כיון דפסול כבעל מום דמי, keivan depasul kiba'al mum
dami, do we say since wormy wood is no good it's like
a מום, mum, או דילמא אין בעל מום אלא בבהמה, o dilma
ein ba'al mum ela bebehema, or that's only by animal? תיקו, teiku,
we don't have an answer. תוספות Tosafot says obviously the reason to
ask it again is even if you assumed it was a problem
by the סולת, solet, the סולת solet is at least clearly a
type of a קרבן, Korban, wood is questionable if you look at
it as a קרבן Korban or just
as firewood, so maybe it
would be a different status.
Okay. So what? Everything's over?
No, we're fine. Okay. So now we are so now we have
done with the flour and now we move on from the flour
to the oil. What type of an oil is used for either
again מנחות menachot in general or at least for the עומר? Omer?
So let's take a look. תקוע, Takoa, תקוע, Takoa, right? Where is
תקוע? Takoa? תקוע, Takoa, excuse me, תקוע. Takoa. Okay.
So where is that located exactly?
I don't know. Where? Somewhere in the שומרון. Shomron. Okay. So תקוע
אלפא לשמן Takoa alfa leshemening is A-grade oil. What? Bethel area. Okay.
Is A-grade oil, תקוע. Takoa. אבא שאול אומר שניה לה,
Abba
Shaul
omer sheniya lah, you know, right second to it, again, doesn't necessarily
mean grade B, maybe A-minus or not A-plus, anyway is רגב בעבר
הירדן, Regev be'ever HaYarden, רגב Regev on the other side of the
Jordan. Now by the way, רגב מן עבר הירדן, Regev min ever
HaYarden, by the way, I was about to say
if this is
עומר Omer this is fascinating because the עומר Omer can only come
from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, not from חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz. So
first of all there's a question about עבר הירדן. Ever HaYarden. The
משנה Mishna in כלים, Kelim, which I do not remember, I mean
I remember talking about it but don't remember what it says, says
that you can't bring ביכורים Bikkurim from עבר הירדן.
Ever HaYarden. I'm trying to remember what it says
about the עומר. Omer. That is the one משנה Mishna that distinguishes
between עבר הירדן Ever HaYarden and what point is it in כלים?
Kelim?
Because כלים Kelim lists ten levels of קדושת ארץ ישראל. kedushat Eretz
Yisrael. It says, let's take
it. Pshetyan? Pshetyan? Ah.
Okay. Would you find it on Wikipedia on your iPod? Google Maps.
Okay, that's a good way. Okay, it says here like this. ארץ
ישראל מקודשת מכל הארצות, Eretz Yisrael mekudeshet mikol ha'aratzot, ומה היא קדושתה?
umah hi kedushatah? How is ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael higher level of
קדושה, kedusha, at least agriculturally or in certain ways, whatever?
שמביאים ממנה העומר והביכורים ושתי הלחם
מה שאין מביאים מכל הארצות.
shemevi'im mimenah ha'omer vehabikkurim
veshtei halechem
mah she'ein mevi'im mikol ha'aratzot. So did it mention עבר הירדן? Ever
HaYarden? So I thought, I'm pretty sure you don't bring ביכורים Bikkurim
from עבר הירדן. Ever HaYarden. The question is whether you can bring
the עומר.
Omer. Any different? Well, ביכורים Bikkurim has more of the idea of
שבח ארץ ישראל shevach Eretz Yisrael than the עומר Omer specifically. Okay,
I have to look that up. One minute. Okay, I'd have to
look that up. So this is interesting because if it is talking
about the עומר, Omer, then it's saying that you can and is
implicitly saying you can bring the oil of the עומר Omer from
עבר הירדן, Ever HaYarden, but let me try to get back to
you about that tomorrow,
the general question
about whether the עומר Omer can come from עבר הירדן. Ever HaYarden.
Okay, כל
הארצות היו כשרות
אלא
מכאן היו מביאים.
Kol ha'aratzot hayu kesherot
ela mikan hayu mevi'im.
So again you could really bring from anywhere, either if, you know,
anywhere in Israel or anywhere in general, depending if it's talking about
the עומר Omer or is it talking about, well the other question
I meant to
raise was, well no, the other question I meant to raise depends
on the context. The other question I meant to raise is we
know the עומר Omer has to come from grain from ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, because it's the whole idea of the ראשית קצירכם, reishit
ktzirchem, you know, of the grain. Does the oil of the עומר
Omer have to come from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is less obvious.
So number one there's a quest besides the עבר הירדן, Ever HaYarden,
there's a question I hadn't had a chance to look at this,
I'll get back to you tomorrow, there's another one, a question whether
the עומר, Omer, whether the oil of the עומר Omer has to
come at all from ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. That's question number one.
Question number two is are we talking about the עומר Omer at
all? Or are we talking about כל מנחות, kol menachot, which is
the question that we've been dealing with all along. Okay, so all
of that is pretty ambiguous, but the point is that these were
the ideal places to get the oil. כל הארצות היו כשרות. Kol
ha'aratzot hayu kesherot. You could really bring from anywhere, אלא מכאן היו
מביאים. ela mikan hayu mevi'im. These are the places that they chose
to bring. Now does the anywhere mean anywhere in Israel or anywhere
in general? If you remember the previous משנה Mishna by the grain
said you could bring it from anywhere, but רש"י Rashi there said
we were talking about the עומר Omer and said anywhere meant anywhere
in... Israel. So anywhere doesn't necessarily mean anywhere. Or was it say
every yard? And he may say ours? It could be! Anyway, so
I think this משנה Mishna number one, as I said before, number
one, the question is, is it only talking about the עומר, Omer,
talking about all things? And number two is even about the עומר,
Omer, I think there's an interesting question which I didn't have a
chance to look into is, are you can you bring the oil
of the עומר Omer from חוץ לארץ? Chutz la'aretz? I'll try to
get back to you on all of that tomorrow. Let's type let's
continue. Okay, אין מביאין לא מבית הזבלים ולא מבית השלהין, Ein mevi'in
lo mibeit hazvalim velo mibeit hashlehin, this just sounds familiar, the same
way the grain can't come from these types of places, the olives
for the oil cannot come from a place that was required either
required or had you know heavy manure fertilization or a place that
required irrigation. You cannot bring olives from there, ולא ממה שנזרע ביניהם,
Velo mima shenizra beinehem, and not from places where there was grain
growing amongst the olive trees. So it's the reverse. You can't bring
grain where trees had grown and can't bring the olive from olive
trees where grain had grown. But any place the grain and the
trees are in competition doesn't help either either crop. Okay, so you
can't bring it from that. ואם הביא כשר, Ve'im hevi kasher, בדיעבד
Bedi'avad it's okay. אין מביאין, Ein mevi'in, just like we said by
the flour. So basically, it's directly parallel to the flour. Again, the
only new question that has come up for us is what types
of issues arise for the עומר Omer in terms of the oil.
Does it have to come from ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? Now it
goes on. אין מביאין אנפקטון, Ein mevi'in anpakton, ואם הביא כשר. Ve'im
hevi kasher. You cannot bring
this אנפקטון, Anpakton, which the גמרא Gemara will explain what it means,
but basically
it is what is it? It is משל עו. Meshel iv. Right,
thank you. It is unripe unripe olives. So you cannot bring from
unripe olives and בדיעבד Bedi'avad it's כשר. kasher. אין מביאין מן הגרגרין
שנשרו במים. Ein mevi'in min hagargerin shenishru bamayim. You cannot use from
olives that have basically been soaked in water before their oil has
been extracted. That obviously makes the oil worse, you know, dilutes it.
ולא מן הכבשים, Velo min hakvashim, or olives that have been that
have been like pickled before the oil has been extracted. ולא מן
השלוקים, Velo min hashlikim, or olives that have been boiled. ואם הביא
פסול, Ve'im hevi pasul, and oil that comes from those olives is
invalid. So again, it's fascinating who told the גמרא Gemara this? Like,
how do we know what type of oil, you know, is invalid?
I mean, by the מנורה Menorah it says שמן זית זך כתית
למאור, Shemen zayit zach katit lama'or, but where do we know what
the standards are for other things? It's similar to the issues that
came up by the wheat. Let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. We have an interesting little story. Okay, so גמרא, Gemara, וישלח
יואב תקועה. Vayishlach Yoav Tekoa. תקוע, Tekoa, excuse me, I did it
wrong again again. תקוע, Tekoa, just shows that I've never been to
תקוע. Tekoa. Okay, וישלח יואב, Vayishlach Yoav, has anybody been there? I
see I see it on the sign somewhere. I see it on
the sign. They spell it with a Q, don't they, on the
sign? Anyway, okay, וישלח, Vayishlach, so anyway, וישלח יואב תקועה ויקח משם
אשה חכמה. Vayishlach Yoav Tekoa vayikach misham isha chachama. So this was
a whole plot that יואב Yoav had to get this woman to
act like she was mourning and have דוד David speak to her
and it was a try to a way to convince דוד David
to you know reconcile with אבשלום Avshalom and take אבשלום Avshalom back.
Okay, so they had a whole little plot there. Anyway, it says
that she was a wise woman. מאי שנא תקוע? Mai shna Tekoa?
Why did he specifically go to תקוע? Tekoa? אמר רבי יוחנן מתוך
שרגילים בשמן זית, Amar Rabbi Yochanan mitoch sheragilim beshemen zayit, because they
have so much olive oil there, it's clear from our משנה, Mishna,
חכמה מצויה בהן, Chochma metzuya bahen, they're very wise because apparently olive
oil was a was a brain food. They say fish oil is
supposed to be a brain food. So anyway, the גמרא Gemara believes
that olive oil was a brain food. Or maybe there's a certain
חכמה chochma in how to prepare the? No, no, no. רש"י Rashi
says there's other גמרות Gemorot that speak about דשמן זית מפקח את
הלב. Deshemen zayit mefake'ach et haleiv. Okay, so what? מפקח את העיניים.
Mefake'ach et ha'einayim. Yeah. All right, so now we have another story.
תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, וטובל בשמן רגלו. Vetovel beshemen raglo. So this
is by the ברכה bracha of אשר. Asher. He dips his leg
in oil. זה חלקו של אשר, Ze chelko shel Asher, this is
the portion of אשר, Asher, clearly that was the ברכה, bracha, שמושך
שמן כמעין. Shemoshech shemen kema'ayan. In אשר Asher's portion, right, the oil
flows. I guess it's in אשר. Asher. Does anybody look at a
map? Let's look at a map. Was it אשר אשמר שבט דן?
Was it Asher ashmar shevet Dan? What? Well, that's a good question.
Let's take a look. We'll Google. We'll find it. Oh. תקוע. Tekoa.
152. 88. It's in the Gush Etzion area that we see. 248.
Oh, then I don't see it. They're not showing where it's dividing.
Oh wait, there is. Israel minute. It looks more here like it's
in the יהודה Yehuda area because it's right under ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Yeah.
And they don't, they don't show תקוע Tekoa in a division of
the שבטים, shevatim, but it looks here like, well let me just
see, let me just see if I can find it. שאר הים,
She'ar HaYam, okay let's just see if we can find the whole
division of the tribes where אפרים Ephraim is. What, אפרים Ephraim first,
you're right, we're just referring to in general. I know, but the
question is it would be nice if that would be, you know
if it would be the same. Okay hold on. Let us just
see where, they don't have the division of the שבטים shevatim anywhere
here? Not crazy. All right, crazy, normally every biblical map atlas has
a picture of the division of the שבטים. shevatim. What, yeah, all
right, we'll have to see. Anyway, where is אשר? Asher? Does anybody
know vaguely where the חלק chelek of אשר Asher is? I'm sorry
to admit that I don't know. Okay, what, I'm real, I was
thinking if, I think more of it back. Let me try one
that I'll do. This is why we can't give up any of
our land. This is why we can't give up any of our
land. Abu-dis at the moment? Well, here, oh no, he's also very
good, the line area towards the south. It didn't, it's got to
be in במדבר ל', Bamidbar Lamed, isn't that where it gets divided,
במדבר ל'? Bamidbar Lamed? It's why it was a separate, yeah, big
time near ים המלח. Yam HaMelach. Oh so that's where אשר Asher
is, around ים המלח? Yam HaMelach? Oh exactly down there. So, so
it's like it's north of ירושלים? Yerushalayim? Oh so north of ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, so תקוע Tekoa is south of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, so unfortunately
it doesn't, that doesn't work out. So let's keep on going. כל
מי שמיטרומגלו kol mi she-mitromaglo I guess not then. Right, all right
תקוע's Tekoa the exception. Anyway, okay so אשר, Asher, the oil, olive
oil flows like a well in a wellspring. אמרו פעם אחת נצרכו
להם אנשי לודקיא, Amru pa'am achat nitzrechu lahem anshei Ludkaya, one time
the people of לודקיא, Ludkaya, which is a non-Jewish city, needed בשמן
בשמן, beshemen beshemen, they had a real need of oil. Is this
part of the story or is it? No, מינו minu so they
appointed מינו להן פולמוסטוס אחד, minu lahen pulmostos echad, a certain officer,
obviously a Greek word, I did not get a chance to also
check up on the exact etymology of that, they appointed an officer.
אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said to him, לך והבא לנו שמן
במאה רבוא. lech ve-havi lanu shemen be-me'ah ribbo. Go buy for us
oil with 100, a רבוא ribbo is 10,000, so 100 10,000 is
a million, for a million מנה, maneh, a million מנה, maneh, מנה
maneh itself is you know, is a large sum of money. So
a billion dollars, whatever, so tons of money they wanted to buy
either a huge quantity and presumably awful high quality. Okay, so הלך
לירושלים. halach li-Yerushalayim. He went to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, of course where do
you go if you're going to go get it from the Jews?
Presumably everything is in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So אמרו לו, amru lo, no,
it's not all in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, לך לצור, lech le-Tzor, go to
צור. Tzor. Now תוספות Tosafot says צור Tzor is not Tyre because
that would not be, you know, because that would not be in
ישראל. Yisrael. So a different צור. Tzor. So anyway, so הלך לצור.
halach le-Tzor. אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said to him, לך לגוש
חלב, lech le-Gush Chalav, go to גוש חלב. Gush Chalav. הלך לגוש
חלב. halach le-Gush Chalav. אמרו לו, Amru lo, לך אצל פלוני. lech
etzel ploni. So גוש חלב Gush Chalav apparently was a place in
אשר Asher and they said go to so-and-so, לשדה הלז, la-sadeh ha-laz,
in that field. ומצאו u-matza'o so הלך, what? גוש חלב is near
מירון. Meron. Aha, which is, which is north, right, okay, so north
east. So anyway to פלוני, ploni, so ולשדה הלז, ve-la-sadeh ha-laz, so
he went, apparently he הלך לשדה הלז, halach la-sadeh ha-laz, he went
to that certain field, ומצאו שהיה עוזק תחת זיתו. u-matza'o she-hayah ozek
tachat zeito. He was either, to debate what the word עוזק ozek
means, he was either removing stones or he was, he was collecting
olives in the olive field. He was doing something there under with
his olive trees. Making fences, whatever he was doing. אמרו לו, Amru
lo, he said to him, יש לך שמן במאה רבוא שאני צריך?
yesh lecha shemen be-me'ah ribbo she-ani tzarich? Do you have oil for
a million dollars? I want to buy a million dollars of oil.
Do you have enough? אמר לו, Amar lo, המתן לי עד שאסיים
מלאכתי. hamten li ad she-asayem melachti. Wait for me to finish what
I'm, you know, I'm working on. המתין עד שסיים מלאכתו. Himtin ad
she-siyem melachto. He waited for him to finish whatever sort of, you
know, fieldwork he was doing. לאחר שסיים מלאכתו, Le-achar she-siyem melachto, after
he finished, הפשיל כליו לאחריו. hifshil kelav leacharav. He put his, you
know, field implements behind him, like in his knapsack. והיה מסקל ובא
בדרך. Vehayah mesakel u-va ba-derech. And he was, as he was going
on the way, he was like removing, you know, stones and like
cleaning up the pathway. So the point is he was doing very
mundane fieldwork type of labor. Okay, both when he found him and
even after he was done with the labor and he was walking
home, he was cleaning up the pathway. אמר לו, Amar lo, יש
לך שמן במאה רבוא? yesh lecha shemen be-me'ah ribbo? He said to
him, or maybe it says he said to himself, you know, but
anyway, he said you really have a million dollars worth of oil?
You're like an עני. ani. כמדומני ששחוק שחקו בי היהודים. Ki medumanni
she-sechok se-chaknu bi ha-Yehudim. I'm thinking the Jews are making, you know,
a mockery of me. They say go here, go there, they send
me to a person, he's a field hand. He hasn't a million
dollars worth of oil? So, okay. כיון שהגיע לעירו, keivan shehigi'a le'iro,
he came to his city, הוציאה לו שפחתו קומקום של חמין. hotzi'ah
lo shifchato kumkum shel chamin. They took out for him like a,
you know, an urn, thank you, of hot water ורחץ בו ידיו
ורגליו. verachatz bo yadav veraglav. So first he, you know, washed himself
off from the dirt of the journey and of the day's labor.
הוציאה לו ספל של זהב. hotzi'ah lo safal shel zahav. They took
him out a gold, you know, whatever ספל, safal, gold, whatever bowl
of some sort anyway מלא שמן, malei shemen, filled with oil וטבל
בו ידיו ורגליו, vetaval bo yadav veraglav, and he used it to
to dip his hands and his feet into this gold bowl filled
with oil לקיים מה שנאמר, lekayeim mah shene'emar, to fulfill the verse
וטובל בשמן רגלו, vetoveil bashemen raglo, and he, you know, he immerses
his his feet in oil. ולאחר שאכלו ושתו, ve'achar she'achlu veshatu, so
they ate and they drank and they had a good meal מדד
לו שמן במאה ריבוא. madad lo shemen beme'ah ribo. He gave him
a million dollars worth of oil. So he had, he had that
much oil. So אמר לו, amar lo, he said to him כלום
אתה צריך ליותר, klum atah tzarich leyoter, oh, is that all you
need, just a million dollars worth? I got some more. Do you
need anymore? אמר לו, amar lo, he said to him הן, hein,
you know, really we do need more אלא שאין לי דמים, ela
she'ein li damim, I have no money left. So אמר לו, amar
lo, if you want to buy more אם אתה רוצה ליקח קח,
im atah rotzeh likach kach, take as much more as you need
ואני עמך ואטול דמיו, va'ani imcha ve'etol damav, and I'll go with
you back until you get home and I'll, you know, you'll pay
me the balance. So, of course, all the point being that he
had even more than a million dollars worth of oil. He had
as much oil as this guy could ever want. מדד לו שמן
בשמונה עשר ריבוא. madad lo shemen bishmonah asar ribo. So he measured
out another 18 ריבוא, ribo, another 180,000, you know, either units of
oil but anyway the way רש"י Rashi says it it's a מנה
maneh which presumably means, you know, amount of money. אמר לו, amar
lo, and he said to him, הניח אותו אמר, heniach oto amar,
excuse me, they said לא הניח אותו איש לא סוס ולא פרד
ולא גמל. lo heniach oto ish lo sus velo fered velo gamal.
That person who had to now transport all this oil did not
leave behind him neither a horse, nor a, nor a donkey, nor
a no mule. פרד fered is a mule, right? A mule or
a camel ולא חמור, velo chamor, or a donkey בארץ ישראל be'eretz
yisrael in Israel שלא שכרו, shelo secharo, that he did not have
to hire to transport all this oil. כיון שהגיע לעירו, keivan shehigi'a
le'iro, he finally came back to his city. יצאו אנשי עירו לקלסו.
yatz'u anshei iro lekalso. They came out to praise him that he
managed to purchase, you know, a million dollars worth of oil that
they thought they would never be able to find this much oil.
אמר להם, amar lahem, he said to them לא לי קלסוני, lo
li kalsuni, do not praise me אלא זה שבא עמי, ela zeh
sheba imi, this person that came with me שמדד לי שמן במאה
ריבוא, shemadad li shemen beme'ah ribo, that he set, he gave me
a hundred, you know, a million dollars worth of oil והרי נושה
בי בשמונה עשר ריבוא. veharei nosheh bi bishmonah asar ribo. Now, not
only that, I owe him another 180,000 because he gave me even
more oil. They have so much oil. לקיים מה שנאמר, lekayeim mah
shene'emar, what? Where's the oil? Where's the oil? Yeah, it was produced
where? They got it from אשר. Asher. No, it's not the oil
we want today. It's like the Jews are very great, they got
all the olive oil they can ever use. It's the petroleum oil
they don't have. Anyway לקיים מה שנאמר, lekayeim mah shene'emar, to fulfill
the פסוק pasuk יש מתעשר ואין כל. yesh mitasher ve'ein kol. There's
somebody who acts rich and really has nothing מתרושש והון רב, mitroshesh
vehon rav, and somebody who appears poor and has great wealth. So
here it started that he was shocked. Look how humble he is,
he's working in the field, he's going to sell me a million
dollars worth of oil, and lo and behold, guess so, not only
do they have all of that oil but they remain, you know,
very humble, which is also part of the story. Okay, nice.